Okay, so I'm going to give you
a quick introduction to CloudFormation
and give you an overview that really allows you
to understand how it works.
So let's create a stack
and let's make sure first of all that we are in the US East,
Northern Virginia, US East 1 region,
because the template I've created for you
only works in that region.
And I will tell you why when we see the template.
So please make sure to switch the region to this one.
Next we create a stack and we have to prepare templates.
So multiple options.
We can choose an existing one,
use a sample template and some samples are provided
or build from Application Composer.
But we're going to choose an existing template.
We're going to upload a template file
and let me show you what the file looks like.
So in your course code under CloudFormation,
you have 0-just-EC2.yaml.
And this is a very simple file right now
which has a resource blog and it creates
an instance called My instance.
The type is EC2 instance,
and then you have a few properties.
The first one is the availability zone,
which is US East 1a
and this is why you have to choose US East 1
as your region in CloudFormation service right now.
And the image ID is this AMI ID.
And as you should know,
AMI IDs are scoped within the region.
So for these two reasons, you must be in US East 1
for this hands-on.
The instance type is T2 micro.
And so as you can see we define how to launch
an EC2 instance through this YAML file.
So let's go ahead and actually upload this file.
So select it and then you can actually view it
in Application Composer.
So open this in a new tab.
So here is my template.
So as you can see, Application Composer gives us
a visual understanding of our templates.
So if we look within templates,
we get back the code that we just uploaded right here
and we can switch it to YAML and JSON if we wanted to.
But in the canvas we see that we have
one standard component,
which is an EC2 instance in my instance.
You could double click on it
and view it the fact that it's an EC2 instance as well.
So Application Composer is a nice way
of getting a visual feedback of your templates.
Anyway, back into our stack.
Let's click on next.
We have to provide a demo stack name.
So I'll call this one demo CloudFormation
and then some parameters.
But because we don't define any parameters
in our templates so far, we don't do anything here.
Let's click on next here we have tags.
So I'm just going to show you tag being CFDemo
just to show you how tags work in CloudFormation.
We scroll down, no permissions to set.
We don't touch these options and neither of these options.
So let's click on next and we review and create.
And when we're good to go, let's click on submit.
So as you can see now this template I uploaded
is going to generate some events and that was very quick.
So the events are done
and this actually created a resource right here,
which is an EC2 instance.
So the code got a resource out of it,
and this is why it's called Infrastructure as Code.
So you can click on this EC2 instance.
As you can see right now in the EC2 console,
my instance is running
and you can check the fact that indeed it is a T2 micro
type of instance.
And you can also check the fact
that the AMI ID we have selected is the one
that was entered in our template.
So this is all very convenient.
On top of it, we notice that if you go to our EC2 instance
and we look at the tags,
we can see that some tags were applied by CloudFormation,
which are the name of the CloudFormation,
the name of the logical ID and the stack ID,
but also the name we have specified.
So the tag we specified has name CFDemo
has also been applied to this EC2 instance,
and therefore it's named correctly.
Okay, so now that we have an instance,
let's go ahead and update this stack.
So we click on update
and we replace the existing template.
And this time we're going to choose this
1-ec2-with-sg-eip file.
And if you have a look at it, this file is right here.
So we have a more complete file now.
We have a parameter section
to set the security group description.
We have the EC2 instance section,
which is a bit more complete
because now it has security groups and it has two of those.
We have an Elastic IP here that is attached to my instance.
And we have one security group here defined for SSH rules.
So port 22 is going to be open
and we have the server security group,
which is going to be open on port 80 from everyone
and port 22 from a very specific IP.
So this is a more complete CloudFormation template.
Now let's go back to CloudFormation
and we're going to apply these template.
So here we are prompted with a parameter.
So what is the security group description?
So let's enter demo description.
And as you can see now we are entering some texts,
which is going to make everything vary.
We don't touch the tags, we don't touch anything.
Let's click on next.
And now because we are applying an update,
as you can see, we have a change set.
And so we can preview the change sets,
which is what is going to change
in our CloudFormation stack.
So as you can see, a few things are added.
There is an Elastic IP, there is an SSH security group
and a server security group.
And it's add, so it's new.
And my instance is going to change,
it's going to be modified, and there is a column here
says replacement true.
That means that this EC2 instance is going to be replaced,
that means that the previous one is going to be deleted
and a new one is going to be created.
So it's good to know in case you had some data
on your EC2 instance.
So now let's submit this update and see what happens.
So CloudFormation is a very smart service
because well, from just this code right here
it's able to figure out exactly what to do
thanks to the change sets,
so it knows exactly what to create first.
So as you can see, the server security group
and the SSH security group already are created.
And only then will it update the EC2 instance.
So now the my instance is an update in progress,
and as you can see, it says requested updates requires
the creation of a new physical resource, hence creating one.
So if you go into the EC2 console
and we remove this filter,
now we see that we have two EC2 instances.
This one was created before and this one is the new one
and it was pending and now it is running.
So a new instance got created
and once it's created, again, it's going to be updated here,
the update is complete.
And now we have MyEIP.
So now the Elastic IP is going to be created
and then attached to my EC2 instance.
So if we're quick and we go on the left hand side
to Elastic IP, even though we may not have seen what it is
here is Elastic IP that is properly created,
properly tagged, and it is attached already
to our EC2 instance.
So now if I click on this one
and then I click on networking at the bottom,
you see Elastic IP address here was attached.
So everything was done by CloudFormation and was done well.
And if you look at CloudFormation now in the events,
as you can see, the Elastic IP was created
and then there was a cleanup in progress due in progress.
So that means that the previous EC2 instance right here,
this one got terminated,
which is very handy because CloudFormation
takes care of everything.
So you can go into the resources tab
and see everything that was created through CloudFormation.
On top of it, if you go to the template
and you click on view in Application Composer,
you're able to see now your new architecture.
So we have an EC2 instance connected to an Elastic IP
and connected to two security groups.
So this is very handy
because it gets a visual representation
again of our templates.
So finally, of course, confirmation.
You could go ahead and delete things manually.
You could delete this Elastic IP and so on,
and the EC2 instances manually.
But this is actually not recommended.
You don't wanna touch anything manually
when using CloudFormation.
Instead, you want to either update the templates,
or if you wanted to delete everything, just click on delete.
And CloudFormation will delete all the stack resources.
And the stack resources are also going to be deleted
in the right orders.
So CloudFormation will figure out what to delete first
and so on to clean up everything.
So CloudFormation is a really powerful service
to do infrastructure as code because it's declarative.
You just say what you want and CloudFormation
figures it out, and all the code will control
your infrastructure, which is very, very handy.
So learning how to use it
and write it can be a very good skill in AWS.
So I hope you liked it
and I will see you in the next lecture.